<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xml:id="ch07">
    <title>Hop Architecture</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Highly Available Hadoop Filesystem (HDFS)</title>
        HDFS is a distributed, fault-tolerant file system designed to run on 
        low-cost commodity hardware.
        HDFS v2 introduced a new highly available metadata architecture, where 
        the entire filesystem's metadata is stored in memory on a single node, and
        changes to the metadata (edit log entries) are also replicated 
        (using a quorum-based algorithm) to a distributed set of log servers. In HDFS v2,
        there is typically a Primary and Secondary NameNode configured, where the 
        Secondary NameNode pulls an eventually consistent copy of the metadata by applying
        edit log entries stored at the log servers.
        <figure id="hadoop2">
            <title>Hadoop v2</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="media/hadoop2.png" scale="70" align="center"></imagedata>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>    
        
        In contrast, Hop HDFS replaces the Primary-Secondary metadata model with a 
        shared atomic transactional memory, implemented using MySQL Cluster.
        In our new model, the size of HDFS' metadata is no longer limited 
        to the amount of memory that can be managed on the JVM of a single node.
        Our solution involves storing the metadata in a replicated, distributed, in-memory
        database that can scale up to several tens of nodes, all while maintaining 
        the consistency semantics of HDFS.  We show how to maintain the consistency of the metadata, 
        while providing high performance. We guarantee freedom from deadlock and progress by, 
        respectively, logically organizing inodes  (and their constituent blocks and replicas) into a hierarchy and having transactions 
        agree on a global order for acquiring both explicit locks and implicit locks on subtrees 
        in the hierarchy. We improve performance by introducing a snapshotting mechanism 
        that minimizes the number of roundtrips to the database and implementing row-level locking
        when updating files and directories. 

        <figure id="hop-hdfs">
            <title>Hop HDFS</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="media/hop-hdfs.png" scale="50" align="center"></imagedata>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>    

    </sect1>

    <sect1>                                
        <title>Early performance measurements for Hop HDFS</title>
        Our early performance figures show that Hop HDFS can scale to handle a similar
        number of read and write requests per unit time as Apache HDFS. We have
        introduced a number of features to enable this high level of performance, including
        a snapshot layer at NameNodes and row-level locking at the database level, rather than
        a system level lock for update operations as is done in Apache HDFS.
        Our snapshotting layer involves a transaction acquiring all resources it requires at
        the start of a primitive filesystem operation, and performing local read/write operations
        on the snapshot copy, and then finally committing or rolling back on transaction commit.
        <figure id="hdfs-snapshot">
            <title>Reduction in number of database roundtrips by introducing snapshotting at NameNodes.</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="media/hdfs-snapshot.png" scale="70" align="center"></imagedata>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>    
        <figure id="hdfs-locking">
            <title>Effect of replacing a global lock with row-level locks.</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="media/hdfs-locking.png" scale="70" align="center"></imagedata>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>            
    </sect1>    
        
    <sect1>
        <title>Hop Architecture</title>
        <para>Hops, as a cloud patform for distrbuted processing and big data, is made up of latest Hadoop ecosystem. As you 
            can see in <xref linkend="arch-stack"/> there are three major layers in our stack, HDFS, YARN and Workflow. 
            Cross-layer aspects like Security and PaaS services are also included.</para>

        <figure id="arch-stack">
            <title>Hop stack</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="media/arch-stack.png" scale="70" align="center"></imagedata>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>    
        <para>.</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>HOP File System (HOP-FS)</emphasis>
                    At the bottom layer of big data stack is HOP-FS a distributed file system based on Hadoop Distributed File System (HDFS). We revisited relational 
                    representation of metadata to remove limitation of single metadata server and single point of failure. Our File System solution can scale up to several tens 
                    of nodes, while maintaining the consistency semantics for the filesystem. We store the metadata on a shared-nothing, in-memory, partitioned database by 
                    maintaining the consistency of the metadata, while providing high performance. HOP-FS also guarantees freedom from deadlock and progress.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>MySQL Cluster</emphasis>
                    MySQL Cluster is a higly scalable, real-time, ACID-complaint transactional database.
                    Designed around a distributed, multi-master architecture with no single point of failure;
                    MySQL Cluster's real-time design delivers predictable, milisecond response times with 
                    the ability to service millions of operations per second. In the case of our data platform, it is
                    used to handle and manage the state of our multi-namenode solution of our architecture.                                    
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>YARN</emphasis>
                    Resource negotiator for managing high volume distributed data processing tasks against HDFS. 
                    It supports different processing models other that Map-Reduce by separating its Resource 
                    Manager from Scheduler and Application Master. Application Master gives us flexibility to 
                    accommodate heterogeneous processes by implementing a wrapper for each kind of application 
                    so it could manage any kind of processing resources that is defined for it. This allows user 
                    to process data intensive task like MapReduce jobs or in our case our future support for 
                    bioinformatic workflow tasks engine which will make use of YARN to handle and negotiate the 
                    scheduling of this type of jobs.                                 
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Workflow Engine</emphasis>
                    On top of YARN, HOPS workflow engine parses workflows into an execution model of arbitrary tasks. 
                    For each task, it asks YARN for a containter, then for each container allocated task based on 
                    the scheduling policy it stages in data into HOPSFS, launches the task and stages out the result 
                    back to HOPSFS                                     
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </sect1>

  
    <sect1>
        <title>Deployment model</title>
        <para>At the moment HOPS supports Amazon Cloud, Open Stack and Bare Metal. Based on the chosen cloud provider, as it can be seen in <xref linkend="arch-deploy"/> our deployment 
            model consist of Hops-Dashboard plus other machines either virtual in cloud or bare metal. Dashboard is the point of administration with web access through which customer 
            could define configuration of the cluster, machines are allocated, their software stack is installed and state of the cluster is monitored. Cloud machines could be associated
            into security node-groups, machines inside each node-group basically have the same security credentials and could communicate with each other; however, communication 
            between machnies from different security group is not possible. All the machins inside the cluster have the same infrastructure and basic stack of softwares, althoug based 
            on the services each machine shoul provide, arbitrary platform softwares are installed.</para>
        <figure id="arch-deploy">
            <title>Deployment Model</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="media/arch-deploy.png" scale="35" align="center"></imagedata>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Platform-as-a-Service Stack</title>
        <para>The Platform-as-a-Service stack describes the set of frameworks and tools
            that we use to deploy a Hadoop cluster on both cloud and bare-metal
            clusters.
            <figure id="arch-helper">
                <title>Hop PaaS stack</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/arch-layers.png" scale="50" align="center"></imagedata>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Hop PaaS Stack</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>SnakeYAML and YAML</emphasis>
                        YAML (YAML Ain't  Markup Language) is markup language which takes concepts from
                        programming languages such as C, Perl and Python, and ideas from XML. YAML syntax
                        allows easy mappings of common data types found in high level languages like list, 
                        associative arrays and scalar. It makes it suitable for tasks where humans are likely to
                        view or edit data structures, such as configuration files or in our case, cluster
                        definition files. Additionally, we make use of the open source parser SnakeYAML to parse
                        the contents of our cluster definition files. Parser transforms the given cluster 
                        definition into consecutive stages such as defining security groups, virtual machine 
                        allocation, bittorent, installation, validation and retry.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Apache JClouds</emphasis>
                        Apache JClouds is an open source multi-api interface which allows easy interaction 
                        with multiple cloud providers and cloud software stacks. This open source api gives 
                        support around 30 providers which include Amazon, Azure, OpenStack and Rackspace. 
                        JClouds offers api implementations both in Java or Clojure. Through they simple 
                        interface, it is very simple to deploy and port your application over different cloud 
                        environments. Each single configuration in YAML may result in multiple JCloud instructions.         
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Chef</emphasis>
                        Chef is a systems and cloud infrastructure automation framework based on Ruby 
                        that simplifies deployment of servers and applications to any physical, virtual or cloud location
                        no matter the size of the infrastructure. The chef-client relies in a series of abstract definitions 
                        (defined as cookbooks and recopes) which are managed in Ruby and are treated like source code.
                        With each definition, we describe how a specific part should be built and managed, which then; the chef-client
                        applies these definitions to deploy and configure servers and applications as specified.
                        In most of the cases, it is simple enough to let chef-client know which cookbooks and recipes
                        it needs to apply.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>BitTorrent</emphasis>
                        After machines are allocated in cloud, with the metadata information that JCloud returns, dashboard
                        tries to open a ssh connection into every single machine and install Chef agent for installations. 
                        Before installation starts, software libraries is replicated in all machines from dashboard, though 
                        the process could overflow the bandwidth to dashboard if all machines try to download from dashboard. 
                        To handle this situation HOPS run a bittorent in which dashboard machine is the seeder, then all 
                        machnies could contribute to download process which is both faster and anti-bottleneck. After download 
                        Chef agent starts installation based on the required packages in each machine and with the order of 
                        dependencies between packages. 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <!--                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Collectd</emphasis>
                        Collectd is a daemon which collects system performance statistics periodically and 
                        provides mechanisms to store values in a variety of ways like RRD files. Collectd 
                        gathers statistics about the system it is running and stores this information. With 
                        these statistics, we can keep track of the performance of your cluster and detect
                        possible failures and performance bottlenecks that might be needed to be address.
                    </para>
                </listitem>-->
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>