<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <para>Hadoop Open Platform-as-a-service, is an effort to offer a high performance next generation
        hadoop platform focusing in improving its scalability, availability and reliability. This section describes
        the information and materials you need in order to start working with our data platform by making use
        of our Hadoop Open PaaS dashboard. HOPS dashboard provides an end-to-end management and 
        monitoring application of our Hadoop distribution operating in the datacenter of your choice. With our
        dashboard, thanks to its graphical user interface (GUI); you will be able to manage your cluster, 
        define the cluster infrastructure of your choice, monitor services and alerts through a centralized application
        You will find here all the necessary information in order to easily deploy our solution in the 
        infrastructure of your choice.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>Basics:</title>
        <para>Hadoop Open Platform-as-a-Service consists of multiple services:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Core Platform:</emphasis> The basic components of our Hadoop distribution.
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Hadoop Distributed File System (HDFS):</emphasis>
                                    Hadoop provides high-throughput access to data in a highly distributed environment. 
                                    In our case our distribution is based on Hadoop version 2 release modified in order to offer 
                                    extended mechanism for more scalable and available namenode.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>MySQL Cluster:</emphasis>
                                    MySQL Cluster is a higly scalable, real-time, ACID-complaint transactional database.
                                    Designed around a distributed, multi-master architecture with no single point of failure;
                                    MySQL Cluster's real-time design delivers predictable, milisecond response times with 
                                    the ability to service millions of operations per second. In the case of our data platform, it is
                                    used to handle and manage the state of our multi-namenode solution of our architecture.                                    
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Open Platform-as-a-Service:</emphasis> 
                        The key components behind our Open Platform-as-a-Service solution.
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Chef:</emphasis>
                                    Chef is a systems and cloud infrastructure automation framework based on Ruby 
                                    that simplifies deployment of servers and applications to any physical, virtual or cloud location
                                    no matter the size of the infrastructure. The chef-client relies in a series of abstract definitions 
                                    (defined as cookbooks and recopes) which are managed in Ruby and are treated like source code.
                                    With each definition, we describe how a specific part should be built and managed, which then; the chef-client
                                    applies these definitions to deploy and configure servers and applications as specified.
                                    In most of the cases, it is simple enough to let chef-client know which cookbooks and recipes
                                    it needs to apply.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>JClouds:</emphasis>
                                    JClouds is an open source multi-api interface which allows easy interaction with multiple cloud providers   
                                    and cloud software stacks. This open source api gives support around 30 providers which include Amazon,
                                    Azure, OpenStack and Rackspace. JClouds offers api implementations both in Java or Clojure.            
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Requirements:</title>
        <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Hadoop Open Platform-as-a-Service Portal:</title>
        <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>How to launch a HOPS Dashboard:</title>
        <para></para>
    </section>
</section>
