<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <para>Hadoop Open Platform-as-a-service, is an effort to offer a high performance next generation
        hadoop platform focusing in improving its scalability, availability and reliability. This section describes
        the information and materials you need in order to start working with our data platform by making use
        of our Hadoop Open PaaS dashboard. HOPS dashboard provides an end-to-end management and 
        monitoring application of our Hadoop distribution operating in the datacenter of your choice. With our
        dashboard, thanks to its graphical user interface (GUI); you will be able to manage your cluster, 
        define the cluster infrastructure of your choice, monitor services and alerts through a centralized application
        You will find here all the necessary information in order to easily deploy our solution in the 
        infrastructure of your choice.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>Basics:</title>
        <para>Hadoop Open Platform-as-a-Service consists of multiple services:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Core Platform:</emphasis> The basic components of our Hadoop distribution.
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Hadoop Distributed File System (HDFS):</emphasis>
                                    Hadoop provides high-throughput access to data in a highly distributed environment. 
                                    In our case our distribution is based on Hadoop version 2 release modified in order to offer 
                                    extended mechanism for more scalable and available namenode.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>MySQL Cluster:</emphasis>
                                    MySQL Cluster is a higly scalable, real-time, ACID-complaint transactional database.
                                    Designed around a distributed, multi-master architecture with no single point of failure;
                                    MySQL Cluster's real-time design delivers predictable, milisecond response times with 
                                    the ability to service millions of operations per second. In the case of our data platform, it is
                                    used to handle and manage the state of our multi-namenode solution of our architecture.                                    
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>YARN:</emphasis>
                                    Resource negotiator for managing high volume distributed data processing tasks against
                                    HDFS. This allows user to process data intensive task like MapReduce jobs or in our case
                                    our future support for bioinformatic workflow tasks engine which will make use of YARN
                                    to handle and negotiate the scheduling of this type of jobs.                                     
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Open Platform-as-a-Service:</emphasis> 
                        The key components behind our Open Platform-as-a-Service solution.
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Chef:</emphasis>
                                    Chef is a systems and cloud infrastructure automation framework based on Ruby 
                                    that simplifies deployment of servers and applications to any physical, virtual or cloud location
                                    no matter the size of the infrastructure. The chef-client relies in a series of abstract definitions 
                                    (defined as cookbooks and recopes) which are managed in Ruby and are treated like source code.
                                    With each definition, we describe how a specific part should be built and managed, which then; the chef-client
                                    applies these definitions to deploy and configure servers and applications as specified.
                                    In most of the cases, it is simple enough to let chef-client know which cookbooks and recipes
                                    it needs to apply.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Apache JClouds:</emphasis>
                                    Apache JClouds is an open source multi-api interface which allows easy interaction 
                                    with multiple cloud providers and cloud software stacks. This open source api gives 
                                    support around 30 providers which include Amazon, Azure, OpenStack and 
                                    Rackspace. JClouds offers api implementations both in Java or Clojure.
                                    Through they simple interface, it is very simple to deploy and port your application
                                    over different cloud environments.            
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>SnakeYAML and YAML:</emphasis>
                                    YAML (YAML Ain't  Markup Language) is markup language which takes concepts from
                                    programming languages such as C, Perl and Python, and ideas from XML. YAML syntax
                                    allows easy mappings of common data types found in high level languages like list, 
                                    associative arrays and scalar. It makes it suitable for tasks where humans are likely to
                                    view or edit data structures, such as configuration files or in our case, cluster
                                    definition files. Additionally, we make use of the open source parser SnakeYAML to parse
                                    the contents of our cluster definition files.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Hadoop Support:</emphasis> 
                        Set of components that allow easy monitoring your hadoop installation.
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Collectd:</emphasis>
                                    Collectd is a daemon which collects system performance statistics periodically and 
                                    provides mechanisms to store values in a variety of ways like RRD files. Collectd 
                                    gathers statistics about the system it is running and stores this information. With 
                                    these statistics, we can keep track of the performance of your cluster and detect
                                    possible failures and performance bottlenecks that might be needed to be address.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Requirements:</title>
        <para>
            In order to make use of our data platform, it is essential that you have a running a copy of our
            dashboard application running in your main machine through one of the supported environments
            we offer, and that machine is has connectivity both to the rest of your cluster or 
            cloud Infrastructure. The following environments are currently fully supported:
        </para>
        <unorderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Amazon Web Services:</emphasis>
                    In order to make use of our platform in this cloud Infrastructure, it is necessary that you provide
                    the credentials for you EC2 account in order to deploy our dashboard application in a Amazon
                    Instance.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </unorderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Hadoop Open Platform-as-a-Service Portal:</title>
        <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>How to launch a HOPS Dashboard:</title>
        <para></para>
    </section>
</section>
