<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xml:id="ch02">
    <title>Portal</title>
    <para>Hadoop Open Platform-as-a-service, is an effort to offer a high performance next generation
        hadoop platform focusing in improving its scalability, availability and reliability. This section describes
        the information and materials you need in order to start working with our data platform by making use
        of our Hadoop Open PaaS dashboard. Hop dashboard provides an end-to-end management and 
        monitoring application of our Hadoop distribution operating in the datacenter of your choice. With our
        dashboard, thanks to its graphical user interface (GUI); you will be able to manage your cluster, 
        define the cluster infrastructure of your choice, monitor services and alerts through a centralized application
        You will find here all the necessary information in order to easily deploy our solution in the 
        infrastructure of your choice.
    </para>

    <example>
        <title>Hop Portal</title>
        <programlisting>https://snurran.sics.se:8181/hop-dashboard</programlisting>
    </example>

    <figure xml:id="portal-login">
        <title>Hop Portal</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="media/portal.png" align="center" width="500" scalefit="1"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>   
    <sect1>
        <title>Requirements:</title>
        <para>
            In order to make use of our data platform, it is essential that you have a running a copy of our
            dashboard application running in your main machine through one of the supported environments
            we offer, and that machine is has connectivity both to the rest of your cluster or 
            cloud Infrastructure. For ease of use, we currently have available our own web portal, 
            that in matter of minutes, will deploy our dashboard. For now, the supported OS in our test bed was
            Ubuntu 12.04 or higher.
            The following environments are currently fully supported:
        
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Amazon Web Services:</emphasis>
                        In order to make use of our platform in this cloud Infrastructure, it is necessary that you provide
                        the credentials for you EC2 account in order to deploy our dashboard application in a Amazon
                        Instance and the minimum recommend Instance type should be at least the resources of an 
                        m1.large type Instance with ubuntu running (our default testing bed used version 12.04)
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>OpenStack</emphasis>
                        In order to make use of our platform in OpenStack, it is necessary that you provide the 
                        credentials and configuration parameters to connect to you OpenStack end-point. The recommend
                        instance to use in you OpenStack infrastructure should be equivalent to a m1.large instance
                        type or greater with an ubuntu based image (our default testing bed used ubuntu 12.04 cloud guest edition)
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Baremetal Physical Machine:</emphasis>
                        It is possible deploy our solution on a physical machine, and; in order to do it you only need
                        to provide us the security credentials and access to the specific machine so we can deploy our 
                        software through SSH with an account with sudo access. The recommended OS for deploying
                        should be ubuntu based (our default testing bed used ubuntu 12.04)
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Vagrant:</emphasis>
                        We also count with support with vagrant deployment. With our vagrant distribution, you can 
                        easily deploy locally in one VM machine a whole cluster using our data platform. Ideal for getting
                        contact and test our platform before trying it in a production environment.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Hop Portal</title>
        <para>
            The Hop web portal, is an entry point were users can test our platform in one of our
            supported environments. It is a simple web application that can deploy our dashboard in Amazon or in
            a private machine of your choice with external connectivity. With our dashboard, later on you can 
            deploy and configure the rest of your cluster using our solution. Once you have the dashboard on 
            environment of your choice, proceed to one of the installation guides found in this manual 
            in the desired environment.
        </para>
    
        <sect2>
            <title>How to launch a Hop Dashboard</title>
            <para>
                Launching a Hop Dashboard is quite simple and takes a couple of minutes, here you may find
                instructions on how to use the dashboard for Amazon EC2 and Baremetal Machine:
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <emphasis>Amazon EC2:</emphasis>
                            In order to deploy our dashboard in Amazon EC2 in the region of your choice follow these 
                            simple steps:
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Login into the HOPS Portal with your user name and password.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        In the new page, select from the providers the Amazon EC2 option. A form will be 
                                        generated
                                    
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                    Dashboard credential, were you specify the admin username and password 
                                                    in order to access your newly created dashboard.
                                                </para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                    EC2 credentials which include the Access Key id from you AWS account with 
                                                    its related Secret key.
                                                </para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                    Configuration parameters that we need to in order to deploy a virtual 
                                                    machine in Amazon with default values that you may want to change:
                                                    <orderedlist>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                Security group where the machine will be deployed. If it does not exist,
                                                                we will create it and open the ports needed for our application.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                The hardware ID of the instance type we want to use from Amazon EC2. 
                                                                For example, m1.small, t1.micro. The recommended instance type is
                                                                m1.large.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                Image ID which includes the region of that image and the ami id tag.
                                                                We only support ubuntu based images.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                Location ID of the region you want to deploy the dashboard.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                Selecting the option to authorize the public key, it will open a new option
                                                                were you can insert your desired public key so you can access the virtual
                                                                machine as by default we generate random key pairs for the machine
                                                                through EC2 key pair service, and it is not possible to access the machine
                                                                internally without this option.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                Selecting the override login user, will override the default user for ubuntu
                                                                AMI images with the login user of your choice. This is necessary if you
                                                                are going to use a custom based ubuntu image which are not one 
                                                                of the Ubuntu images that canonical offer in Amazon by default.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                    </orderedlist>
                                                </para>
                                            </listitem>
                                       
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <figure xml:id="portal-aws">
                                            <title>Portal AWS</title>
                                            <mediaobject>
                                                <imageobject>
                                                  <imagedata fileref="media/portal-AWS.png"
                                                  scalefit="1" align="center" scale="50"/>
                                                </imageobject>
                                            </mediaobject>
                                        </figure> 
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        To start the process after filling up the form, press the launch instance button. 
                                        The whole process will probably take between 10-15 minutes on average. In the end,
                                        you will receive a notification showing the address were you can access the Dashboard
                                        in your browser and its private ip address. To login, use the credentials you specified
                                        previously in the portal.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <emphasis>OpenStack:</emphasis>
                            In order to deploy our dashboard in OpenStack of your choice follow these 
                            simple steps, note this is in alpha state:
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Login into the Hop Portal with your user name and password.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        In the new page, select from the providers the Amazon EC2 option. A form will be 
                                        generated.
                                    
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                    Dashboard credential, were you specify the admin username and password 
                                                    in order to access your newly created dashboard.
                                                </para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                    OpenStack credentials, the user name to access the OpenStack project and 
                                                    its password. The username should be a concatenation of the OpenStack 
                                                    project name and the user for that project. For example "projectName:user".
                                                    Also you should indicate the url of your OpenStack Nova end-point in order 
                                                    to send the requests to your OpenStack infrastructure.
                                                </para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                    Configuration parameters that we need to in order to deploy a virtual 
                                                    machine in OpenStack with default values that you may want to change:
                                                    <orderedlist>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                Security group where the machine will be deployed. If it does not exist,
                                                                we will create it and open the ports needed for our application.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                The hardware ID of the instance type we want to use in OpenStack. 
                                                                This is a number which corresponds to the type of instance you want 
                                                                to deploy and is supported by your OpenStack infrastructure 
                                                                We recommended using a configuration similar to a m1.large in EC2.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                Image ID corresponding to the id of the image located in the openstack
                                                                project you want to deploy the dashboard.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                Location ID of the project you want to deploy the dashboard.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                Selecting the option to authorize the public key, it will open a new option
                                                                were you can insert your desired public key so you can access the virtual
                                                                machine as by default we generate random key pairs for the machine
                                                                through OpenStack key pair service, and it is not possible to access the machine
                                                                internally without this option.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                Selecting the override login user. This is necessary for OpenStack if you
                                                                are going to use a custom based ubuntu image.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                    </orderedlist>
                                                </para>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <figure xml:id="portal-openstack">
                                            <title>Portal OpenStack</title>
                                            <mediaobject>
                                                <imageobject>
                                                  <imagedata fileref="media/portal-OpenStack.png"
                                                  align="center" scalefit="1" scale="50"/>
                                                </imageobject>
                                            </mediaobject>
                                        </figure> 
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        To start the process after filling up the form, press the launch instance button. 
                                        The whole process will probably take between 10-15 minutes on average. In the end,
                                        you will receive a notification showing the address were you can access the Dashboard
                                        in your browser and its private ip address. To login, use the credentials you specified
                                        previously in the portal.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </para>
                        <note>
                            <title>IP pools in OpenStack</title>
                            <para>
                                In order to deploy successfully a dashboard in OpenStack, it is necessary that you have allocated
                                at least 1 public IP in that project. During the deployment phase we will query the OpenStack
                                project and link the public ip to the created VM.
                            </para>
                        </note>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <emphasis>Baremetal Physical Machine:</emphasis>
                            In order to deploy our dashboard in a physical machine of your choice follow these 
                            simple steps:
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        Login into the Hop Portal with your user name and password.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        In the new page, select from the providers the Amazon EC2 option. A form will be 
                                        generated were you need to fill in the following:
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                    Dashboard credential, were you specify the admin username and password 
                                                    in order to access your newly created dashboard.
                                                </para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                    SSH credentials which include the host address of the machine we want to
                                                    connect to and the private key to connect.
                                                </para>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                    Extra parameters that we might need:
                                                    <orderedlist>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                Selecting the option to authorize the public key, it will open a new option
                                                                were you can insert your desired public key to allow extra access to the 
                                                                machine.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                        <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                Selecting the override login user, here you fill the name of the sudo user
                                                                to use to deploy our dashboard on the machine.
                                                            </para>
                                                        </listitem>
                                                    </orderedlist>
                                                </para>
                                            </listitem>
                                       
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <figure xml:id="portal-baremetal">
                                            <title>Portal OpenStack</title>
                                            <mediaobject>
                                                <imageobject>
                                                  <imagedata fileref="media/portal-Baremetal.png"
                                                  align="center" scale="30"/>
                                                </imageobject>
                                            </mediaobject>
                                        </figure> 
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        To start the process after filling up the form, press the launch instance button. 
                                        The whole process will probably take between 10-15 minutes on average. In the end,
                                        you will receive a notification showing the address were you can access the Dashboard
                                        in your browser and its private ip address. To login, use the credentials you specified
                                        previously in the portal.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
