<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xml:id="ch02">
    <title>Hop Web Portal</title>

    <para>Hop is an effort to offer a high performance next generation hadoop platform focusing on
        high scalability, availability and reliability. This section describes the information
        needed to jump start Hop cluster. Hop web portal, is an entry point were users can test our
        platform in one of the supported environments: AWS, OpenStack and Baremetal machines. It is
        a simple web application that deploys the Hop Dashboard in the cloud. Using the Hop
        dashboard you can provision and configure the rest of the cluster. Hop Dashboard provides a
        centralized end-to-end management and monitoring application for Hop distribution. Following
        are the step by step instructions for setting up the cluster in different environments. </para>

    <example>
        <title>HOP Portal</title>
        <programlisting>https://snurran.sics.se:8181/hop-portal</programlisting>
    </example>

    <figure xml:id="portal-login">
        <title>Hop Portal</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="media/portal.png" align="center" width="350" scalefit="1"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>   
    <sect1>
        <title>Requirements:</title>
        <para>Hop Dashboard has to be installed on a machine in a cluster that has connectivity both
            to cloud infrastructure and the cluster. Using Hop Web Portal you can provision a
            cluster and install the dashboard to any of the following plateforms: AWS, OpenStack and
            cluster of bare-metal hosts. The following environments are currently fully supported: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Amazon Web Services:</emphasis> In order to use of our platform in
                        AWS cloud Infrastructure, it is necessary to provide EC2 account
                        credentials. When deploying our Dashboard in EC2, we recommend minimum
                        Instance type should be of m1.large type Instance with Ubuntu. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>OpenStack</emphasis> For using Hop on OpenStack, it is necessary
                        that you provide the credentials and configuration parameters to connect to
                        you OpenStack end-point. The recommended instance to use in OpenStack
                        infrastructure should be equivalent to a m1.large instance type or greater.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Baremetal Physical Machine:</emphasis> For deployment on Baremetal
                        machines our system requires security credentials of a user with sudo access
                        to the machines to deploy the software through SSH .</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Vagrant:</emphasis> With our vagrant distribution, you can deploy
                        the whole cluster locally in a VM machine. It is ideal for testing the
                        platform before deployment in a production environment. </para>
                    <para>All the environments are tested with instances running Ubuntu 12.04.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Installing the Hop Dashboard</title>
        <para>Intalling Hop Dashboard through the Portal is quite simple and takes a couple of
            minutes to deploy. Here you may find instructions on how to deploy the dashboard on AWS,
            OpenStack and Baremetal Machine: <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Amazon EC2:</emphasis> For installing the dashboard in Amazon EC2
                        follow these simple steps: <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para> Login into the HOP Portal with your user name and password.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para> Select from the providers option in the maintoolbar, the
                                    Amazon EC2 option. Enter the following information in the new form<itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Dashboard credentials: admin's username and
                                                password in order to access your newly created
                                                dashboard. </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>EC2 credentials which include the Access Key id
                                                from you AWS account with its related Secret key.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Instance configuration parameters used to deploy a
                                                virtual machine in AWS.<orderedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para>Security group where the machine will be
                                                  deployed. If it does not exist, then a new
                                                  security group will be created automatically.
                                                  </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para>The hardware ID of the instance type we want
                                                  to use from Amazon EC2. For example, m1.small,
                                                  t1.micro. The recommended instance type is
                                                  m1.large. </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para>Image ID which includes the region of that
                                                  image and the <emphasis>ami id</emphasis> tag. We
                                                  only support Ubuntu based images. </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para>Location ID of the region you want to deploy
                                                  the dashboard. </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para>Selecting the option to authorize the public
                                                  key will open a new option dialog box were you can
                                                  insert your public key. By default we generate
                                                  random key pairs for the machines through EC2 key
                                                  pair service, and it is not possible to access the
                                                  machines internally without this option. </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para>Selecting the override login user, will
                                                  override the default user for Ubuntu AMI images
                                                  with the login user of your choice. This is
                                                  necessary if you use custom Ubuntu images which
                                                  are not one of the Ubuntu images that canonical
                                                  offer in AWS by default. </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                </orderedlist>
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                    <figure xml:id="portal-aws">
                                        <title>Portal AWS</title>
                                        <mediaobject>
                                            <imageobject>
                                                <imagedata fileref="media/portal-AWS.png" align="center"  scale="40"/>
                                            </imageobject>
                                        </mediaobject>
                                    </figure>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>After filling up the form, press the Launch Instance button.
                                    The whole process takes 10-15 minutes. After the deployment you
                                    will receive a notification showing the URL of the newly
                                    deployed Hop Dashboard. To login the dashboard, use the
                                    credentials you specified previously in the web portal.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>OpenStack:</emphasis> For deployment in OpenStack cloud follow
                        these simple steps. Note, this is in alpha state: <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para> Login into the Hop Portal with your user name and password.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para> Select from the providers the OpenStack option. A new form
                                    will be generated. <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>Dashboard credentials: here you specify the admin
                                                username and password for the new dashboad. </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>OpenStack credentials: the user name and password
                                                to access the OpenStack project. The username should
                                                be a concatenation of the OpenStack project name and
                                                the user for that project. For example
                                                "projectName:user". Also you should indicate the url
                                                of your OpenStack Nova end-point in order to send
                                                the requests to your OpenStack infrastructure.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para> Configuration parameters that are used to deploy
                                                a virtual machine in OpenStack: <orderedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para>Security group where the machine will be
                                                  deployed. If it does not exist, we will
                                                  automatically create a security group and open the
                                                  ports needed for the application. </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para>The hardware ID of the instance type we want
                                                  to commission in OpenStack cloud. This is a number
                                                  which corresponds to the type of instance you want
                                                  to deploy and is supported by your OpenStack
                                                  infrastructure. We recommended using a
                                                  configuration similar to a m1.large in EC2.
                                                  </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para>An Image ID image located in the openstack
                                                  project. </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para>Location ID identifies the dashboard in the
                                                  OpenStack cluster.  </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para>Selecting this option to authorize the
                                                  public key based access. It will open a new dialog
                                                  box were you can insert your desired public key.
                                                  By default we generate random key pairs for the
                                                  machine through OpenStack key pair service, and it
                                                  is not possible to access the machine internally
                                                  without selecting this option. </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para>Selecting the override login user: This is
                                                  necessary for OpenStack if you are using a custom
                                                  Ubuntu image. </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                </orderedlist>
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                    <figure xml:id="portal-openstack">
                                        <title>Portal OpenStack</title>
                                        <mediaobject>
                                            <imageobject>
                                                <imagedata fileref="media/portal-OpenStack.png" align="center" scale="40"/>
                                            </imageobject>
                                        </mediaobject>
                                    </figure>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>After filling up the form, press the Launch Instance button.
                                    The whole process takes 10-15 minutes. After the deployment you
                                    will receive a notification showing the URL of the newly
                                    deployed Hop Dashboard. To login the dashboard, use the
                                    credentials you specified previously in the web portal </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist></para>
                    <note>
                        <title>IP pools in OpenStack</title>
                        <para>It is necessary that you have allocated at least 1 public IP to the
                            project. During the deployment phase the portal will query the OpenStack
                            project and link the public ip to the VM. </para>
                    </note>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Baremetal Physical Machine:</emphasis> For deploying the dashboard
                        on a BareMetal hosts cluster follow these simple steps: <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para> Login into the Hop Portal with your user name and password.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para> In the new page, select BareMetal from the providers list. A
                                    form will be generated were you need to fill in the following <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para> Dashboard credentials: here you specify the admin
                                                username and password for the new dashboad. </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para> SSH credentials: includes the host address of the
                                                machine we want to connect to and the private key.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para> Extra parameters that we might need: <orderedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para> Selecting the option to authorize the
                                                  public key, it will open a new option were you can
                                                  insert your desired public key to allow extra
                                                  access to the machine. </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                  <para>Selecting the override login user will
                                                  rename the sudo user to used to deploy the
                                                  dashboard on the machine. </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                </orderedlist>
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </itemizedlist>
                                    <figure xml:id="portal-baremetal">
                                        <title>Portal Baremetal</title>
                                        <mediaobject>
                                            <imageobject>
                                                <imagedata fileref="media/portal-Baremetal.png" align="center" scale="40"/>
                                            </imageobject>
                                        </mediaobject>
                                    </figure>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>After filling up the form, press the Launch Instance button.
                                    The whole process takes 10-15 minutes. After the deployment you
                                    will receive a notification showing the URL of the newly
                                    deployed Hop Dashboard. To login the dashboard, use the
                                    credentials you specified previously in the web portal. </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
