<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="ch03">
    <title>Hop Dashboard</title>
    
    <para>Hop Dashboard is a web application designed with Hadoop administrators in mind. The
        Dashboard provides a centralized end-to-end management and monitoring application for Hop
        clusters. It simplifies the Hadoop administrator's job by having all the necessary
        statistics of the Hadoop cluster gathered in one place and presented in an effective
        manner.</para>
    <para>Certain parameters need to be configured when the Hop Dashboard is launched for the first
        time. In order to access the dashboard, use the credentials you specified in the Hop Portal
        during dashboard deployment <xref linkend="ch02"/>. After the login, press the user icon,
        and a menu with the following options will pop up: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para> Change password </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> Edit Graphs </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> Backup/Restore </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> Setup Credentials </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist> We will go these options in more detail in the following sections. </para>
    <sect1>
        <title>Change Password</title>
        <para>Change the password for this user.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="edit_graphs">
        <title>Edit Graphs</title>
        <para>The Hop Dashboard enables the customization of what monitoring data that is displayed
            to the administrators. An administrator can select which graphs to enable for the
            different services of Hop. You can define new graphs or import the list of graphs from a
            file.  <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>New</emphasis> Selecting this option will open a new dialog where
                        you can define the specifications for a new graph for statistics monitored
                        by the dashboard. </para>
                    <figure xml:id="dash-new-graphs">
                        <title>Graph Editor</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="media/dash-new-graphs.png" align="center"
                                    width="500"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Import</emphasis> It is also possible to import a predefined set
                        of graphs from a JSON file. This is the quickest way to load a large number
                        of graphs. </para>
                    <!--                    <figure xml:id="dash-import-graphs">
                        <title>Import Graphs</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="media/dash-import-graphs.png" align="center"
                                    scale="50"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                    </figure>-->
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>The graph specifications are stored in a MySQL database and loaded in the
            dashboard. The graph table shows all the graphs for a specific type of service or a
            component that the dashboard is monitoring. Pressing the zoom button will generate a
            dialog box where you can see more details about the graph. </para>
        <figure xml:id="dash-selected-graphs">
            <title>Graph Selection Detail</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="media/dash-detail-graphs.png" align="center" width="500"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Backup/Restore</title>
        <para>The Dashboard's state is stored entirely in a MySQL database instance. This option
            makes a backup of the whole dashboard state as an SQL file that can be downloaded by the
            user for off-site backup. In the case of failure or maintenance, the dashboard can
            restore a previous state from a backup SQL file. </para> 
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Setup Credentials</title>
        <para>The administrator need to specify user credentials that are used when the dashboard
            deploys a cluster on a cloud platform or cluster. They are typically AWS or OpenStack
            credentials or a public key for cluster deployments. If user credentials have not been
            setup, cluster deployment will fail.</para>   
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <title>Cluster Management</title>
        <para>Cluster management is an interesting feature in the Hop Dashboard. The dashboad keeps
            track of different cluster applications deployed in the cloud. It allows the
            administrators to create, edit, delete, load and export clusters. </para>
        <figure xml:id="dash-manage-cluster">
            <title>Manage Cluster</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="media/dash-manage-cluster.png" align="center" width="500"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Create Cluster:</emphasis> Selecting this option will take you
                        to the cluster generation wizard where a users can of generate their own
                        clusters for Hop. In the next chapter, we will explain in detail how users
                        can create their custom clusters using our Cluster Definition Language, see
                        <xref linkend="defining_a_cluster">Chapter: Defining a Cluster</xref>. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Delete Clusters:</emphasis> This option will delete a selected
                        cluster. It is possible to delete multiple clusters at once by shift
                        clicking multiple clusters before selecting this option. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Edit Selected Cluster:</emphasis> This option will allow a user
                        to edit an existing stored cluster. Administrators can use this wizard to
                        modify the set of hosts or services in an existing cluster. They can edit
                        the cluster either by re-running the cluster wizard or by choosing to use
                        the embedded YAML editor available in the dashboard.</para>
            <para>
                If we select the online editor option, it will open the selected cluster 
                into a YAML editor window.
            </para>
            <figure>
                <title>YAML Editor</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                                <imagedata fileref="media/dash-yamleditor.png" align="center"
                                    width="500"/>
                            </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
                        
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Load Selected Cluster:</emphasis> This option allows the user to
                        load an existing cluster definition from a YAML file. This is a useful
                        feature for reusing cluster definitions, users can share cluster definitions
                        and load them using this option.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Export Cluster:</emphasis> It saves the information about the
                        cluster in a YAML file, so that the cluster definition can be shared. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Cluster Deployment Progress</title>
        <para>The Hop Dashboard monitors all the nodes deployed in its clusters. It displays the
            history of all the nodes going through different phases of the deployment cycle. A
            progress bar appears over each of the entries in the table showing the deployment
            progress of the nodes. A cluster node goes through the following phases during
            deployment: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Waiting:</emphasis> A task has been generated in the node
                        scheduler but no node creation query has been sent to the cloud
                        provider.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Creation:</emphasis> The scheduler has submitted the query to
                        the cloud provider and it is waiting for the cloud provider to finish
                        deploying the virtual instance. When an instance is successfully created an
                        initialization script is executed for preliminary configuration of the node.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Install:</emphasis> After the node is successfully commissioned,
                        chef installs recipes for Hop Services to fetch the necessary binaries from
                        the different repositories. This phase is optional in case of using pre
                        built virtual instances which contain Hop binaries. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Configure:</emphasis> A node in this phase means, that; the node
                        is receiving the configuration script which will execute chef with the
                        selected recipes for the services defined for that node. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Complete:</emphasis> The node has successfully finished
                        executing the configuration script with chef and it is now part of the
                        working cluster. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Retrying:</emphasis> The deployment system has detected a
                        problem during a node deployment phase and it is retrying to recover from
                        the failure. It retries the failed phase script for five times.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Error:</emphasis> When all the retires are exhausted the node is
                        marked erroneous. Hadoop administrator can to take further actions to
                        recover the node, for example, SSH into the failed node and the fix the
                        problem manually, retry the deployment process or delete the failed
                        nodes.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist><figure>
                <title>Clusters Progress</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/dash-clusters-progress.png" align="center"
                            width="500"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Monitoring</title>
        <para>Hop Dashboard monitors hosts, alerts and Hop services in real time. A brief overview
            of the monitoring tools is given below. </para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Hosts</title>
            <para>The host monitoring tool shows the state of all the nodes in the clusters. An
                administrator can track information of his/her interest such as the allocated IPs
                for the nodes, host names, host IDs, health of the nodes, and when the last
                heartbeat was received from the nodes. It also monitors available resources on the
                nodes such as the number of cores that machine has, average load on the instance,
                disk usage and physical memory in use. </para>
            <figure>
                <title>Hosts</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/dash-hosts.png" align="center" width="700"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>   
            <para>Selecting the host ID's displays a detailed view of the host's analytics with the
                graphs. See the <xref linkend="edit_graphs"/> section to create or delete graphs for
                the dashboards monitoring components. </para>
            <figure>
                <title>Hosts Details-Services</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/dash-host-detail.png" align="center" width="700"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <title>Hosts Details Graphs</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/dash-host-detail-2.png" align="center" width="700"
                        />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>     
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Alerts</title>
            <para>This feature allows the user to view alerts for events of interest to the administrator,
                such as failed hosts, full hard drives, etc. An administrator can filter alerts of certain
                severity and that were generated in a certain time window. The Alerts feature is based on 
                collectd thresholds.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Alerts</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/dash-alerts.png" align="center" width="700"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>    
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Clusters</title>
            <para>The cluster monitoring tool gives a bird eye view of the clusters monitored by the Hop
                Dashboard. It contains information such as the nodes that compose the cluster
                and the health status of the services deployed on those nodes. 
                Also it keeps track of the resources allocated
                to the cluster such as total number of cores which compose the overall computing
                power of the cluster, the total disk capacity and the total physical memory
                capacity. An administrator can drill down into a cluster to find out the list of services
                in the cluster, their status and a list of nodes in each service.  
                Many services can be restarted from the Dashboard.
            </para>
            <figure>
                <title>Clusters</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/dash-clusters.png" align="center" width="700"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>   
            <figure>
                <title>Detailed Cluster View</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="media/dash-cluster-detail.png" align="center"
                            width="700"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <sect3>
                <title>YARN monitoring</title>
                <para>The Hop Dashboard displays graphs on YARN performance analytics. </para>
                    <figure>
                <title>YARN Metrics</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="media/dash-YARN-metrics.png" align="center"
                                width="700"/>
                        </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>You can also access performance analytics for the resource and node managers in
                    YARN. </para>
            <figure>
                <title>Resource Manager Metrics</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="media/dash-YARN-resource.png" align="center"
                                width="700"/>
                        </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <title>Node Manager Metrics</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="media/dash-YARN-manager.png" align="center"
                                width="700"/>
                        </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The Hop dashboard provides direct access to the resource and node manger web UIs
                    provided by the Apache distribution. The resource manager web UI gives detailed
                    information about the number of applications submitted, number of applications
                    in progress, number of application completed, total available memory, memory
                    consumed, dead nodes etc. The Node manager web UI displays information such as
                    total memory allocated to the java virtual machine on the node, memory allocated
                    to each container, node health status, Hadoop version, etc. </para>
            
            <figure>
                <title>Resource Manager UI</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="media/dash-YARN-resourceUI.png" align="center"
                                width="700"/>
                        </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>  
               <figure>
                <title>Node Manager UI</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="media/dash-YARN-managerUI.png" align="center"
                                width="700"/>
                        </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure> 
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>MySQL Cluster</title>
                <para>You can monitor the MySQL Cluster using the Hop Dashboard. Its keeps track of data memory, index
                    memory, number of reads and writes per second and number of scans per second. 
                    Data nodes, management nodes, and MySQL servers can all be restarted
                    from the Dashboard.
                </para>
                 <figure>
                <title>MySQL Cluster Monitor</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="media/dash-MYSQL-graphs.png" align="center"
                                width="700"/>
                        </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
                 <para>The dashboard provides a command-line terminal to directly run SQL commands
                    on a MySQL Server connected to NDB.</para>
                  <figure>
                <title>MySQL Console</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="media/dash-MYSQL-console.png" align="center"
                                width="500"/>
                        </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Hop HDFS Console</title>
                <para>The dashboard provides a command-line terminal for executing HDFS operations
                    using the HDFS client. It perform operations such as ls, mkdir, cat, etc.
                </para>
                <figure>
                <title>Hdfs Console</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="media/dash-HOP-console.png" align="center"
                                width="500"/>
                        </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Launching the Hop Cluster </title>
        
        <para>After installing the Hop Dashboard on a machine in the cloud, you can easily deploy
            and manage the Hop Cluster using the dashboard. </para>
        <para>Login the dashboard using the credentials provided to Hop Portal during the installation
            of the dashboard. <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Select the manage cluster option available in the dashboard. </para>
                    <para>
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>Main Menu Bar</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Manage Cluster</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Load File</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Load a file containing the cluster definition. We refer to section
                        <emphasis><xref linkend="defining_a_cluster">Defining a
                            Cluster</xref></emphasis> to create custom clusters definitions.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The file is loaded and the cluster launcher will appear showing the content of
                        the loaded file.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Pressing the <emphasis>Start Cluster</emphasis> button to start the deployment
                        process. A status bar will appear showing information about the current status
                        of the deployment process. Installation process is long and it depends on the
                        number of nodes in the cluster. On average, for 8 nodes it takes around 35
                        minutes. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If a node fails then the Hop cluster launcher will automatically retry the
                        node deployment.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Summary of all the install nodes and their status is displayed after the
                        Cluster Launcher finishes.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist></para>
        <para> Congratulations, you have successfully deployed a Hop cluster ready! </para>
        
    </sect1>
    
   
</chapter>
