<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xml:id="ch04">
    <title>Defining a Cluster</title>

    <para>In this section, we describe the tools we offer in order to easily define and structure
        HOP clusters for their deployment through our orchestration architecture.
        In here, we will introduce you to our definition language to define clusters for cloud
        providers like Amazon EC2 and OpenStack or Baremetal clusters based on physical machines.
        With our cluster definition language, you will see that you will easily have a cluster
        deployed in a matter of minutes by making use of technologies like Chef that will be in
        charge of orchestrating the nodes while we provision them with Jclouds (in the case of a
        virtual environment) or a simple SSH client for your baremetal machines. </para>
    <sect1>
        <title>Cluster Definition Language</title>
        <para>We will start first by presenting our Cluster Definition Language (CDL) with which you
            can defining your clusters with ease. In general, we handle the following abstractions: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Cluster:</emphasis> A cluster is an entity that defines a whole
                        system based on a heterogenous structure composed of multiple nodes. In most
                        of the cases, we can classify the nodes into groups depending of the
                        software they run. To allow further customization of your cluster, we allow
                        interesting options like the possibility of running chef recipes globally on
                        all the nodes and open ports that you may want to be open. In order to identify which type
                        of cluster you are defining, it is necessary to specify the class tag of the
                        type of cluster so our software can map with the bindings of the type of cluster you want
                        to deploy.<example>
                            <title>Defining Global Properties</title>
                            <programlisting>
!!se.kth.kthfsdashboard.virtualization.clusterparser.Cluster
##name of your cluster
name: test2
##enable install phase
installPhase: true
##global parameters
global:
##user defined recipes
  recipes: 
  - ssh 
  - chefClient
## extra ports you want to open
  authorizePorts: 
  - 3306
  - 4343 
  - 3321
                            </programlisting>
                        </example>
                        <note>
                            <title>Git Repositories</title>
                            <para>If you want further customization, it is possible to fork our git
                                repository and customize our chef recipes if you want to modify some
                                parameters of our cluster. Also you can add your own recipes if you
                                decide to launch other services on your code. Simply add this
                                snippet of code under global parameters. <example>
                                    <title>Defining Git repository</title>
                                    <programlisting>
git:
  user: Jim Dowling
  repository: https://ghetto.sics.se/jdowling/hops-chef.git
  key: notNull
                                    </programlisting>
                                </example>
                            </para>
                        </note>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Services:</emphasis> We identify multiple services, in our case
                        related to Hop platform. You can spread this services quite easily among
                        different nodes just indicating that information when grouping them. Also
                        you may indicate further services to be deployed on them.
                        <programlisting>
services: 
  - datanode 
  - nodemanager
  number: 2

                        </programlisting>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Provider:</emphasis> In the case of defining a cluster to be
                        deployed in a virtualized environment through an Amazon EC2 infrastructure
                        or an OpenStack environment, you can give information of the image you want
                        to use, the type of instance to request, login credentials in case you are
                        using custom images. <example>
                            <title>Defining Cloud Providers</title>
                            <programlisting>
provider:
  ##name of the provider, use aws-ec2 or openstack-nova  
  name: aws-ec2
  ##if EC2 use a value to one of EC2 types, in OpenStack this is an id number of the 
  ##type of instance you want to use
  instanceType: m1.large
  ## indicate the login user of the machine with sudo access, necessary for custom images
  ## or openstack image
  loginUser: ubuntu
  ## image you want in EC2 or OpenStack
  image: eu-west-1/ami-35667941 
  ##region of EC2 or project name in OpenStack
  region: eu-west-1
                            </programlisting>
                        </example>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            We will also see that the syntax differs on whether are designing your cluster towards a 
            virtualized environment or a physical environment. In the following sections, we will go through 
            detailed examples for both types of clusters.
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Structuring your Cluster:</title>
        <para> Before using our tools, it is important that you have an idea of how you
            want to structure the services of our data platform through out the whole cluster. 
            In our case, a fully functional cluster requires the
            following services deployed in different machines: <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>MySQL Cluster:</emphasis>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>MySQL-NDB:</emphasis> Your cluster should contain at
                                    least 2 instances of NDB </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>MySQL-MGM:</emphasis> Your cluster should contain at
                                    least 1 instance of a Management Server. </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>MySQL-Mysqld:</emphasis> Your cluster should contain
                                    at least 1 instance of a MySQL Server. </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>HOP</emphasis>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Namenode:</emphasis> Your cluster should contain at
                                    least 2 namenode instances of our Hadoop Solution. </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Datanode:</emphasis> Your cluster should contain at
                                    least 2 datanode instances of our Hadoop Solution. </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Data processing</emphasis>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>ResourceManager:</emphasis> Your cluster should
                                    contain at least 1 resource manager instances of YARN. </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>NodeManager:</emphasis> Your cluster should contain at
                                    least 2 node manager instances of YARN. </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Spark:</emphasis> Your cluster should contain at least
                                    one instance of Spark if you want to do data processing through
                                    Spark to submit your jobs to the system. </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist></para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist><note>
                <title>Multiple Services per Node</title>
                <para>The previous section gave a very simple overview of the components that are
                    needed for a HOP cluster to work correctly. It is possible to allocate various
                    services in one machine or group of machines as we will see in the following
                    sections. </para>
            </note>
        </para>
        <para>Now that we have a general perspective of how a cluster looks like, the next step is
            to identify the environment of your choice for the cluster you want to work with. In the
            following sections, we will describe how you can define the structure for virtualized
            cloud providers like Amazon EC2 and OpenStack or in a physical Baremetal environment. </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Building your cluster:</title>
        <para>
            In this section, we will explain through a couple of complete examples how to define your cluster 
            for Amazon EC2, OpenStack or Baremetal. We will show you how to write your cluster from scratch
            using your own YAML file or you can use the available cluster wizard in order to generate your 
            desired cluster. 
        </para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Cluster in AWS</title>
            <para>
                Lets imagine that we want to define a complete HOP cluster which will contain a basic minimal setup.
                In this case we need 2 NDBs, 1 MGM and 1 Mysqld for the MySQL cluster, 2 namenode and 2 
                datanode for the Hadoop File System, 1 resource manager and 2 node managers for YARN. 
                How we could map the services using only 7 machines?
                A very simple configuration is shown below. Note that the syntax differs slightly from
                the example presented in Chapter 1, but both forms represent valid YAML syntax.
                <example>
                    <title>Full AWS Cluster Example</title>
                <programlisting>
!!se.kth.kthfsdashboard.virtualization.clusterparser.Cluster
name: test2                 
provider:
  name: aws-ec2
  instanceType: m1.large
  loginUser: ubuntu
  image: eu-west-1/ami-35667941 
  region: eu-west-1

##lists of groups, with the roles the nodes 
##will have and open ports 
nodes:
- services: 
  - ndb::dn
  number: 2

- services: 
  - ndb::mgm
  number: 1
	  
- services: 
  - ndb::mysqld
  - hop::namenode
  number: 1
          
- services: 
  - hop::namenode
  - hop::resourcemanager
  number: 1
          
- services: 
  - hop::datanode
  - hop::nodemanager
  number: 2

                </programlisting>
                </example>
                With this configuration file, we will create 5 security groups which will have as a name the first
                service defined in the list. This will also open the ports for those security groups. It will install
                the defined services for each of the nodes in that specific group of nodes.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Cluster in OpenStack</title>
            <para>
                Taking the previous case for Amazon EC2, we can easily write the same cluster description using the
                same cluster definition file. In this case, the only section we need to change is related to the provider
                we want to use which in this case is OpenStack. The file will look as follows:
                <example>
                    <title>Full OpenStack Example</title>
                <programlisting>
!!se.kth.kthfsdashboard.virtualization.clusterparser.Cluster
name: nova             
provider:
  name: openstack-nova
  instanceType: 7
  loginUser: ubuntu
  image: 0190f9c4-d64e-4412-ab88-4f9fd1d7c2e3 
  region: RegionSICS
          
##lists of groups, with the roles the nodes 
##will have and open ports 
- services: 
  - ndb::dn
  number: 2

- services: 
  - ndb::mgm
  number: 1
	  
- services: 
  - ndb::mysqld
  - hop::namenode
  number: 1
          
- services: 
  - hop::namenode
  - hop::resourcemanager
  number: 1
          
- services: 
  - hop::datanode
  - hop::nodemanager
  number: 2
                    
                </programlisting>
                </example>
                With this configuration file, it is possible to deploy the same cluster we defined in Amazon EC2
                without any major changes. You only need to change the provider specifications to match the
                details of your OpenStack Infrastructure.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Cluster on Baremetal Machines</title>
            <para>
                How would we describe the same cluster for Amazon EC2 in a cluster of physical machines?
                In this case it is much simpler but you need to watch out for minor details like, for example;
                the class tag needs to be different for this type of clusters as we will see. Also in this case, you
                need to provide the IP addresses of the machines to connect to. An example is as follows:
                <example>
                    <title>Full Baremetal Example</title>
                <programlisting>
!!se.kth.kthfsdashboard.virtualization.clusterparser.Baremetal
name: baremetal
loginUser: ubuntu
totalHosts: 7
nodes:
  - services: 
    - ndb::dn
    hosts: 
    - 10.20.0.8 
    - 10.20.0.11
	  
  - services: 
    - ndb::mgm
    hosts: 
    - 10.20.0.6
	  
  - services: 
    - ndb::mysqld
    - hop::namenode
    hosts: 
    - 10.20.0.7
	  
  - services: 
    - hop::namenode
    - hop::resourcemanager
    hosts: 
    - 10.20.0.12 
    - 10.20.0.14
	  
  - services: 
    - hop::datanode
    - hop::nodemanager
    hosts: 
    - 10.20.0.16 
    - 10.20.0.17
                </programlisting>
                </example>
                With this configuration file, it is possible to deploy the same cluster we defined in Amazon EC2
                without any major changes. You only need to change the provider specifications to match the
                details of your OpenStack Infrastructure.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Cluster Generator on Dashboard</title>
            <para>
                Apart of offering a mechanism were users can upload their clusters written in YAML to the system
                and later on deploy them, we also have a cluster wizard which allows the user to define a
                cluster step by step quite easily. To make use of this feature, follow these steps:
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Go to the manage cluster section from the main bar in the dashboard. Select the create cluster
                            option.
                                <menuchoice>
                                    <guimenu>Main Menu Bar</guimenu> 
                                    <guisubmenu>Manage Cluster</guisubmenu>
                                    <guimenuitem>Create cluster</guimenuitem>
                                </menuchoice>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            A dialog appears allowing you to select which type of cluster you want to use:
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        <emphasis>Virtualized:</emphasis> Choose this option if you want to deploy
                                        a cluster in Amazon EC2 or OpenStack.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>
                                        <emphasis>Baremetal:</emphasis> Choose this option if you want to deploy
                                        a cluster in physical machines.
                                    </para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                            <figure xml:id="dash-clusterType">
            <title>Select Cluster Type:</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                                        <imagedata fileref="media/dash-clusterType.png" scale="60"
                                            align="center"/>
                                    </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Selecting an option, will bring you to the cluster generator wizard. Here you can select
                            the same options like if you where writing your own file from scratch. You will go through different
                            phases.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            <menuchoice>
                                <guimenu>Cluster Wizard</guimenu>
                                <guisubmenu>Common</guisubmenu>
                                <guisubmenu>Provider (not for Baremetal)</guisubmenu>
                                <guisubmenu>Groups</guisubmenu>
                                <guisubmenu>Confirmation</guisubmenu>
                            </menuchoice>
                        </para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Common Section:</emphasis>
                                    In this section, a form appears were you can select the following options:
                                    <orderedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Name:</emphasis>Name of the cluster
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Provider:</emphasis>Select the type provider between Amazon EC2 or OpenStack, this option is 
                                                available if we create a virtualized cluster.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Git parameters:</emphasis>
                                                Git repository section where you can specify as an option your own git 
                                                repository based on our code. This way you can customize  our recipes or even 
                                                add your own.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Global Recipes:</emphasis>
                                                You can specify chef recipes that you want to execute in all
                                                the nodes
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Global Ports:</emphasis>
                                                Additional Ports to open for your cluster, this option is only available for 
                                                virtualized clusters.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </orderedlist>
                                    <figure xml:id="dash-common-cluster">
            <title>Common Cluster Options:</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                                                <imagedata fileref="media/dash-cluster-common.png"
                                                  scale="50" align="center"/>
                                            </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure xml:id="dash-bare-cluster">
            <title>Bare Metal Common Cluster Options:</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                                                <imagedata fileref="media/dash-bare-common.png"
                                                  scale="50" align="center"/>
                                            </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Provider Section:</emphasis>
                                    This form enables you to define the parameters for OpenStack or Amazon EC2.
                                    Some values appear by default in the case of Amazon EC2 of defining a cluster to be
                                    used with this cloud provider.
                                    <orderedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Instance Type:</emphasis>
                                                The type of instance you want to use in Amazon EC2 or in OpenStack. Note
                                                that in OpenStack we use the id number of the type of instance, not the name.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Image:</emphasis>
                                                The name of the image we want to use the in Amazon EC2 or in OpenStack
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Login user:</emphasis>
                                                Here you include the user name with sudo access to access the instances
                                                in Amazon EC2 or OpenStack. Note that this value is necessary if you use a 
                                                custom AMI in Amazon EC2 or using you use OpenStack.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Region:</emphasis>
                                                Here you include the region you want to deploy in Amazon EC2 or the project
                                                to use in your OpenStack infrastructure.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </orderedlist>
                                    <figure xml:id="dash-provider-cluster">
            <title>Cluster Provider Options:</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                                                <imagedata fileref="media/dash-cluster-provider.png"
                                                  scale="50" align="center"/>
                                            </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Group Section:</emphasis>
                                    In this section you can specify the group of nodes for you cluster with the
                                    their services and ip addresses (if you are deploying a baremetal cluster)
                                    <orderedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Main Service:</emphasis>
                                                The main service you want to deploy in this group of nodes
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Bittorrent Support:</emphasis>
                                                If you want to enable bittorrent sync of binaries from the dashboard.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Number of nodes:</emphasis>
                                                Number of nodes that will contain the same set of services.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Extra Services:</emphasis>
                                                Other services you may want to run which can be also your own services.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Chef Attributes:</emphasis>
                                                In this section, you would include a chef json which will contain the attributes
                                                you may want to override from your recipes.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Ports:</emphasis>
                                                Extra ports that you may want to enable in that group, in this case this only
                                                affect virtualized clusters.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                            <para>
                                                <emphasis>Hosts:</emphasis>
                                                List of hosts IP addresses for the nodes that will be part of this group of nodes.
                                                In this case this option is only available for Baremetal clusters.
                                            </para>
                                        </listitem>
                                    </orderedlist>
                                    <figure xml:id="dash-groups-cluster">
            <title>Cluster Group:</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                                                <imagedata fileref="media/dash-cluster-groups.png"
                                                  scale="50" align="center"/>
                                            </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure>
            <title>Bare Metal Groups:</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                                                <imagedata fileref="media/dash-bare-groups.png"
                                                  scale="50" align="center"/>
                                            </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>    
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Confirmation Section:</emphasis>
                                    In this section you will see a summary of the details of you cluster file.
                                    When you press the submit button, your cluster file will be stored in the dashboard
                                    and it will proceed to the cluster launcher.
                                     <figure xml:id="dash-cluster-confirmation">
            <title>Confirmation:</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                                                <imagedata
                                                  fileref="media/dash-cluster-confirmation.png"
                                                  scale="50" align="center"/>
                                            </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>   
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
          
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
        </sect2>
    
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Wrap up</title>
        <para>
            To summarize this section, in here we have seen the main building blocks that we need to define
            a cluster using our cluster domain specific language. We also explained how you can define your clusters by writing your
            own cluster file through multiple examples and also showed an alternative way of defining cluster
            through the cluster generator wizard which is accessible from the dashboard.
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
