<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xml:id="defining_a_cluster">
    <title>Defining a Cluster</title>

    <para>
        Hops allows you to define a cluster in a single YAML file. A cluster
        definition consists of a provider (cloud or bare-metal), a number of nodes and 
        a set of services deployed on those nodes.
        The benefit of having a cluster defined in a single file is that you can
        now share it with others, who launch the same cluster or modify the file
        and launch a changed version of your cluster, and you can edit it to 
        reconfigure your cluster. 
        </para>
        <para>A cluster definition file consists of the following sections: 
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>[Global]</listitem>
                <listitem>[Provider]</listitem>
                <listitem>Nodes 
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>Services</listitem>
                        <listitem>Number|Hosts</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

         In the example cluster definition file presented in Chapter 1, we showed
         a minimal cluster definition, that had some default values not specified
            in the cluster definition file. There was no <emphasis>Global</emphasis>
            section, and it wasn't stated where the implementations of the services
            came from.
            In <xref linkend="complete-cluster-defn"/>, we give the complete version
            of the cluster definition file. We can see that by default, ssh, chef,
            and collectd are installed on all nodes, and that the chef recipes for
            installing the services are taken from https://github.com/hopstart/hop-chef.git.
            Users can fork the chef recipes we provide,
            customizing and storing them in their own git repository. Soon, we
            will provide support for users specifying their own recipes as 
       </para>                    
       <para>                    
            The file below also shows the full set of defaults for our AWS instances. Currently,
            we only support compute instances. Each services section can be
           further customized with a chefAtttributes section, containing parameters
           for the chef recipes.
       </para>                    
                        <example xml:id="complete-cluster-defn">
                            <title>Complete Example Cluster Definition in Hop</title>
                            <programlisting>
!!se.kth.dashboard.virtualization.clusterparser.Cluster
name: simpleCompleteCluster                 

global:
    services: [ssh, chef, collectd]
    authorizePorts: [22, 4343, 3321]
    git-user: jdowling
    git-repository: https://github.com/hopstart/hop-chef.git
    git-key: /home/jdowling/.ssh/id_rsa

provider:
    name: aws-ec2
    instanceType: m1.large
    loginUser: ubuntu
    image: eu-west-1/ami-35667941 
    region: eu-west-1

nodes:
    - services: 
      - ndb::dn
      number: 2

    - services: 
      - ndb::mgm
      number: 1

    - services: 
      - ndb::mysqld
      - hop::namenode
      number: 1

    - services: 
      - hop::namenode
      - hop::resourcemanager
      number: 1

    - services: 
      - hop::datanode
      - hop::nodemanager
      number: 2
                            </programlisting>
                        </example>


        <para>
       It is possible to take the above cluster definition and deploy the
       same set of VMs and services on an OpenStack cluster. To do this,
       we need to modify the Provider section.
            <emphasis>Provider:</emphasis> You need to specify the infrastructure provider,
            the image you want to use, the type of instance to request, 
            and login credentials in case you are using custom images.

       In the example below, we show how to change the provider section to 
       prepare the cluster definition file to work for OpenStack.
            <example>
                <title>OpenStack provider</title>
                <programlisting>
provider:
name: openstack-nova
instanceType: 7
loginUser: ubuntu
image: 0190f9c4-d64e-4412-ab88-4f9fd1d7c2e3 
region: RegionSICS
                </programlisting>
            </example>
        </para>

        <para>
            We can also deploy the same cluster on bare-metal hosts in a cluster.
            In this case, you need to provide the IP addresses of the machines 
            where the services will be installed. Deploying on bare-metal 
            requires specifying a new clusterparser (se.kth.dashboard.virtualization.clusterparser.Baremetal)
            as well as removing the provider section, and 
            specifying IP addresses in the services sections, instead of number
            of nodes.
        </para>
            <example>
                <title>Bare-metal cluster</title>
            <programlisting>
!!se.kth.dashboard.virtualization.clusterparser.Baremetal
name: baremetal
loginUser: ubuntu

nodes:
- services: 
- ndb::dn
hosts: 
- 10.20.0.8 
- 10.20.0.11

- services: 
- ndb::mgm
hosts: 
- 10.20.0.6

- services: 
- ndb::mysqld
- hop::namenode
hosts: 
- 10.20.0.7

- services: 
- hop::namenode
- hop::resourcemanager
hosts: 
- 10.20.0.12 
- 10.20.0.14

- services: 
- hop::datanode
- hop::nodemanager
hosts: 
- 10.20.0.16 
- 10.20.0.17
            </programlisting>
            </example>


    <sect1>
        <title>Cluster Wizard</title>
        <para>
            In addition to being able to define a cluster in YAML, you can also 
            generate a cluster using a wizard with the following these steps:
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Press the create cluster button following the menu items:
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>Main Menu Bar</guimenu> 
                            <guisubmenu>Manage Cluster</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Create cluster</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        A dialog appears allowing you to select which type of cluster you want to use:
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Virtualized:</emphasis> Choose this option if you want to deploy
                                    a cluster in Amazon EC2 or OpenStack.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>
                                    <emphasis>Baremetal:</emphasis> Choose this option if you want to deploy
                                    a cluster in physical machines.
                                </para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                        <para>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="media/dash-clusterType.png"
                                               align="center" scale="66"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </para>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Selecting an option, will bring you to the cluster generator wizard. Here you can select
                        the same options like if you where writing your own file from scratch. You will go through different
                        phases.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>Cluster Wizard</guimenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Common</guisubmenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Provider (not for Baremetal)</guisubmenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Groups</guisubmenu>
                            <guisubmenu>Confirmation</guisubmenu>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <emphasis>Common Section:</emphasis>
                                In this section, a form appears were you can select the following options:
                                <orderedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Name:</emphasis>Name of the cluster
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Provider:</emphasis>Select the type provider between Amazon EC2 or OpenStack, this option is 
                                            available if we create a virtualized cluster.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Git parameters:</emphasis>
                                            Git repository section where you can specify as an option your own git 
                                            repository based on our code. This way you can customize  our recipes or even 
                                            add your own.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Global Recipes:</emphasis>
                                            You can specify chef recipes that you want to execute in all
                                            the nodes
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Global Ports:</emphasis>
                                            Additional Ports to open for your cluster, this option is only available for 
                                            virtualized clusters.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </orderedlist>
                                <figure xml:id="dash-common-cluster">
                                    <title>Common Cluster Options:</title>
                                    <mediaobject>
                                        <imageobject>
                                            <imagedata fileref="media/dash-cluster-common.png"
                                                       align="center" scale="50"/>
                                        </imageobject>
                                    </mediaobject>
                                </figure>
                                <figure xml:id="dash-bare-cluster">
                                    <title>Bare Metal Common Cluster Options:</title>
                                    <mediaobject>
                                        <imageobject>
                                            <imagedata fileref="media/dash-bare-common.png"
                                                       align="center" scale="50"/>
                                        </imageobject>
                                    </mediaobject>
                                </figure>
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <emphasis>Provider Section:</emphasis>
                                This form enables you to define the parameters for OpenStack or Amazon EC2.
                                Some values appear by default in the case of Amazon EC2 of defining a cluster to be
                                used with this cloud provider.
                                <orderedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Instance Type:</emphasis>
                                            The type of instance you want to use in Amazon EC2 or in OpenStack. Note
                                            that in OpenStack we use the id number of the type of instance, not the name.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Image:</emphasis>
                                            The name of the image we want to use the in Amazon EC2 or in OpenStack
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Login user:</emphasis>
                                            Here you include the user name with sudo access to access the instances
                                            in Amazon EC2 or OpenStack. Note that this value is necessary if you use a 
                                            custom AMI in Amazon EC2 or using you use OpenStack.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Region:</emphasis>
                                            Here you include the region you want to deploy in Amazon EC2 or the project
                                            to use in your OpenStack infrastructure.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </orderedlist>
                                <figure xml:id="dash-provider-cluster">
                                    <title>Cluster Provider Options:</title>
                                    <mediaobject>
                                        <imageobject>
                                            <imagedata fileref="media/dash-cluster-provider.png"
                                                       align="center" scale="50"/>
                                        </imageobject>
                                    </mediaobject>
                                </figure>
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <emphasis>Group Section:</emphasis>
                                In this section you can specify the group of nodes for you cluster with the
                                their services and ip addresses (if you are deploying a baremetal cluster)
                                <orderedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Main Service:</emphasis>
                                            The main service you want to deploy in this group of nodes
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Bittorrent Support:</emphasis>
                                            If you want to enable bittorrent sync of binaries from the dashboard.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Number of nodes:</emphasis>
                                            Number of nodes that will contain the same set of services.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Extra Services:</emphasis>
                                            Other services you may want to run which can be also your own services.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Chef Attributes:</emphasis>
                                            In this section, you would include a chef json which will contain the attributes
                                            you may want to override from your recipes.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Ports:</emphasis>
                                            Extra ports that you may want to enable in that group, in this case this only
                                            affect virtualized clusters.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
                                        <para>
                                            <emphasis>Hosts:</emphasis>
                                            List of hosts IP addresses for the nodes that will be part of this group of nodes.
                                            In this case this option is only available for Baremetal clusters.
                                        </para>
                                    </listitem>
                                </orderedlist>
                                <figure xml:id="dash-groups-cluster">
                                    <title>Cluster Group:</title>
                                    <mediaobject>
                                        <imageobject>
                                            <imagedata fileref="media/dash-cluster-groups.png"
                                                       align="center" scale="50"/>
                                        </imageobject>
                                    </mediaobject>
                                </figure>
                                <figure>
                                    <title>Bare Metal Groups:</title>
                                    <mediaobject>
                                        <imageobject>
                                            <imagedata fileref="media/dash-bare-groups.png"
                                                       align="center" scale="50"/>
                                        </imageobject>
                                    </mediaobject>
                                </figure>    
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                <emphasis>Confirmation Section:</emphasis>
                                In this section you will see a summary of the details of you cluster file.
                                When you press the submit button, your cluster file will be stored in the dashboard
                                and it will proceed to the cluster launcher.
                                <figure xml:id="dash-cluster-confirmation">
                                    <title>Confirmation</title>
                                    <mediaobject>
                                        <imageobject>
                                            <imagedata
                                                fileref="media/dash-cluster-confirmation.png"
                                                align="center" scale="50"/>
                                        </imageobject>
                                    </mediaobject>
                                </figure>   
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>

            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
