<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Installation on AWS</title>

    <para>
        In this section, we will explain furthers steps that are required to deploy a whole functional
        cluster running our data platform through the dashboard. Also we refer to recommendations and aspects you
        should consider before deploying a cluster.
    </para>

    <sect2>
        <title>Pre-requisites:</title>
        <para>
            Before starting, make sure that you have access to a functional and running Dashboard in a virtual
            machine in an accessible Amazon EC2 region. If you have not done so, please refer back to the 
            <xref linkend="ch02"/>.
        </para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
        <title>Requirements:</title>
        <para>
            In order to install and deploy a cluster, you need to define before the structure of the cluster which
            includes specifying the number of machines to create in EC2 with the specific instance type with the 
            specific software. This can be done using a cluster definition file that can be done from scratch or 
            using the embedded wizard available on the dashboard. Further information about describing a cluster
            can be found on the cluster configuration section. Before continuing make sure that you have the 
            following.
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Cluster definition for EC2 (see related section) in a file or loaded from the dashboard 
                        database.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Amazon EC2 credentials to deploy the cluster in Amazon, configured in the dashboard. 
                        In order to do it, select the option setup credentials found in you user icon to specify the 
                        EC2 credentials to be used by the dashboard.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <note>
                <title>Additional dashboard credentials</title>
                <para>
                    It is possible to include other options when deploying an EC2 cluster, for example; for
                    maintanance purposes you might want to authorize extra public keys to the virtual machines.
                    This is possible to set in the credential section of the dashboard.
                </para>
            </note>
        </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
        <title>Launching the cluster</title>
        <para>
            Once we have the dashboard configured with the Amazon EC2 credentials, you can proceed to 
            launch a cluster:
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Select the manage cluster option available in the dashboard.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>Main Menu Bar</guimenu> 
                            <guisubmenu>Manage Cluster</guisubmenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Load File</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        In this new view, you can manage available clusters that you may have defined 
                        previously. You can select a previous cluster, create a new one with the only wizard or
                        load a cluster from a cluster definition file. For further information on managing cluster files, 
                        see <xref linkend="ch04"/>. To continue, select a cluster from the table or load a
                        cluster from a file.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The file is loaded and the launcher view should appear. Here you can view the contents
                        of the cluster to be deployed before launch.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Pressing the start cluster will start the deployment process. A status bar will appear giving
                        information of the current status of the deployment. Also a progress table on the background will be generated
                        with information of the configuration state of the nodes. The process is long and it depends
                        on the number of nodes you deploy. On average, for 8 nodes it takes around 35 minutes.
                    </para>
                    <note>
                        <title>Error Nodes</title>
                        <para>
                            It is possible that some nodes will have issues during the deployment of our software (package configuration problem,
                            erratic behaviour) which in this case our system will detect and will retry to relaunch the software
                            on that specific machine automatically. The maximum number of retries specified for each node
                            is 5, after that; the node will be tagged as an error node and it is possible to do a manual retry
                            after the whole process has finished.
                        </para>
                    </note>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        When the process completes, it will take you back to the progress view where you can see
                        details of the cluster deployment. If nodes failed, you can select those nodes and try to recover
                        them using the retry nodes option.
                    </para>
                    <note>
                        <title>Retrying Nodes</title>
                        <para>
                            Retrying node is an option that helps bringing back nodes that had minor issues when installing packages,
                            were to slow to finish the configuration phase or the default number of retries we use were not enough. 
                            It will not bring back nodes which had a 
                            critical configuration failure, which in this case it will be necessary to log in directly through SSH
                            to the specific machine in order to fix it.
                        </para>
                    </note>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            Congratulations, if everything went okay; you have succesfully deployed a complete cluster ready to use!
        </para>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
