<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="ch01">

    <title>Quickstart with Vagrant</title>
    <para>
        This section describes the steps required to deploy a HOP cluster 
        on a single machine using git, vagrant
        <footnote>
            <para>  
                <link  xlink:href="http://www.vagrantup.com">Vagrant is a tool for building complete development environments.
                    With an easy-to-use workflow and focus on automation,
                    Vagrant lowers development environment setup time, increases development/production parity,
                    and makes the "works on my machine" excuse a relic of the past.</link> 
            </para>
        </footnote>
        , and chef
        <footnote>
            <para>
                <link  xlink:href="http://docs.opscode.com/">Chef is a systems and cloud infrastructure automation framework that makes it 
                    easy to deploy servers and applications to any physical, virtual, 
                    or cloud location, no matter the size of the infrastructure.</link> 
            </para>
        </footnote>
        .
    </para>

    <sect1>
        <title>Pre-requisites:</title>
        <para>
            You should have the following programs installed:
            git and vagrant. You will also need to download the vagrant virtual machine image
            for Ubuntu 12.04 "precise".
            <programlisting>
    apt-get install git-core vagrant
    vagrant box add "precise64" http://files.vagrantup.com/precise64.box
            </programlisting>
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Launching Vagrant</title>
        <para>
            You are ready to clone the chef recipes, and launch a vagrant instance.
        </para>
        <informalexample>
            <programlisting>
    git clone https://github.com/hopstart/hop-chef.git
    cd hop-chef
    vagrant up
            </programlisting>
        </informalexample>
<para>        
        Now grab a coffee, assuming you have a good network connection, 
        it will take around 15 minutes to provision a vagrant instance.
        When vagrant successfully completes provisioning using chef, 
        use the following URL and default user credentials to access the Hop Dashboard:
</para>
        <programlisting>
    https://localhost:9191/hops-dashboard/
    user: admin
    password: admin
        </programlisting>
        <para>
        You can log into the VM and then get root access using:
        </para>
        <programlisting>
    vagrant ssh
    sudo su
        </programlisting>
        <para>
        If needed, you can configure the glassfish webserver here:
        </para>
        <programlisting>
    https://localhost:5858
    user: admin
    password: admin
        </programlisting>        
        <para>
        You can now jump to <xref linkend="ch03">Chapter 3</xref>
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
